Guide to the Megan Cornish Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Megan Cornish papers
1970-2003
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
6259
6259-001
Cornish, Megan
10.26 cubic feet 9 boxes
Papers of one of the first female electricians for Seattle City Light and labor activist
Megan (pronounced MEG-on) Cornish grew up in various locations around the United States. Cornish moved to Washington state after earning her BA from Cornell University in 1969. Cornish worked at the Shelter Half antiwar G.I. Coffee House in Tacoma; and was an active supporter of the United Construction Workers Association (UCWA); and picketed on behalf of striking University of Washington clerical and maintenance workers--part of the Staff Organizing Committee (later the United Workers Union-Independent). Cornish was also an active member of Radical Women, a socialist feminist organization co-founded by Clara Fraser in Seattle.
Fraser was selected to organize an Electrical Trades Trainee (ETT) program at Seattle City Light, she recruited Cornish and dozens of other feminist movement activists to apply. Cornish was hired along with nine other women as ETT employees.
The ETT women’s struggle with City Light management and sometimes with the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers Union, Local 77 to hire women and challenge workplace sexism was hard fought. Cornish, along with her Radical Women colleagues Heidi Durham and Teri Bach, pushed the hardest and were targeted for some of the worst backlash. In the process, Cornish broke through a number of barriers. She became only the second female operator and the first female power dispatcher at Seattle City Light. Eventually promoted to senior power dispatcher, Cornish helped found the Committee for Equal Rights at City Light (CERCL) and, in 1991, was named Active Advocate of the Year, along with her longtime colleague Heidi Durham, by Washington Women in the Trades. She retired in 2004 after thirty years at City Light.
Cornish remains a committed member of Radical Women and the Freedom Socialist Party (FSP), as well as an antiwar activist and an environmental advocate. She has written numerous articles, pamphlets, and a few books on a range of topics over the last 30 years, which have been published by the Freedom Socialist Party publishing arm, Red Letter Press.
Text based on Megan Cornish oral history interview, Cornish, Megan interview with Nicole Grant and Alex Morrow "Radical Women; Freedom Socialist Party; Electrical Trades Trainee (ETT) Program, Seattle City Light," Seattle Civil Rights & Labor History Project < http://depts.washington.edu/civilr/cornish.htm>
Records collected by Megan Cornish on her role as a member of the Electrical Trades Trainees program of female electricians at City Light. The papers include organizing files and legal files from Cornish and other ETT’s discrimination case against City Light. Cornish was also a co-founder and member of the ETT's Committee for Equal Rights at City Light (CERCL).
Closed until processed. Contact Special Collections for more information.
Donated by: Megan Cornish.
Special Collections holds similar materials in these collections:
Clara Fraser papers (Collection No. 3187)
Tyree Scott papers (Collection No. 5245)
George Hammer papers (Collection No. 6276)
Cornish, Megan$vArchives; Seattle City Light$xEmployees$vArchives; Women electric industry workers$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vArchives; Sex discrimination in employment$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$xHistory$vSources; Affirmative action programs$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$xHistory$vSources; Seattle City Light$xHistory$vSources; Electric industry workers$xTraining of$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vSources; Apprenticeship programs$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$xHistory$vSources; Labor$zWashington (State)$zSeattle; Business correspondence; Records (Documents); Periodicals; Ephemera; Course materials; Instructional and educational works; Newspaper clippings; Files (document groupings); Bulletins; Newsletters; Legal documents; Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor Unions; Women; Public Utilities; Seattle
- Electrical Trades Trainees, 1970-1978 (Box 1)
  Correspondence, reports, clippings, candidate lists, memos, fact sheet, policy manual, subpoena, job announcements and descriptions, program schedule, pamphlet, notes, handbooks, contract amendments, records for the ETT case, legal documents including deposition of Carole Coe, press releases, ETT program evaluations, requests for certification, trainee evaluations, newsletters, articles,
- City Light Walkout, 1974 (Box 1)
  Clippings, leaflet
- Electrical Trades Trainees: Case and Media, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  Clippings, memos
- Clara Fraser Case, 1974-1983 (Box 2)
  Proposals, meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, ETT working committee documents, directories, statement by Janet Schokke, timelines, direct and cross examinations of Daisy Jones, Rhuebottom, and Fraser, questionnaire on Darlene Allison, legal documents, Local 77 resolution, notes, clippings, memos, case history, financial reports, Fraser's resume and a biographical sketch, benefit leaflets, press releases, list of supporters, and articles relating to Clara Fraser's employment and termination from Seattle City Light.
- Clara Fraser Case, 1980 (Box 3)
  clippings, articles and a documentary album
- City Light and Employee Trades Training, 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  Memos, correspondence, mailing list, newsletters, clippings and articles, meeting minutes, reports, IBEW Local 77 resolution and other documents, documents and articles relating to Nick Daniggelis, fact sheets, documents relating to Teri Bach's suspension, civil service rules, trainee feedback, training catalog, documents relating to the Uhlman recall committee, proposed Bill of Rights, Eleven Member Committee report, notes, documents relating to Heidi Durham's case, and job description
- City Light and Employee Trades Training, 1975-1982 (Box 4)
  Correspondence, certificate, claim for damages, memos, legal documents, list of labor organizations, KIRO report, clippings, documents relating to Lori Lakshas case, articles, notes, press release, Bill of Rights, invitations, button, documents relating to Heidi Durham, workshop schedule and notes, sexual harassment questionnaire (blank), documents relating to Buzz Jackson's termination, personnel action form, reports, employee evaluation, newsletter, IBEW Local 77 resolutions, contract proposals, meeting minutes, documents relating to Women in Trades, union proposals, IBEW contract with City Light, exam results,
- City Light and Employee Trades Training, 1976-1979 (Box 5)
  Correspondence, clippings and articles, notices, blank helper exam, memos, reports, notes, employee evaluations, Local 77 resolution and dues receipt, City of Seattle Affirmative Action plan, Seattle Personnel Ordinance, legal documents, exam answer sheet, meeting minutes, Local 77 contract proposals, and agreements between IBEW and City Light
- Committee for Equal Rights at City Light (CERCL), 1983-1993 (Box 5)
  Correspondence, memos, legal documents, resume, notes, reports on the Human Rights Department, reports, city ordinance, newsletters, clippings, meeting agendas, and minutes, news releases, resolutions, draft of Affirmative Action Plan, memos from City of Seattle Employees Against Discrimination, flyers, petition, and Seattle ordinance
- Committee for Equal Rights at City Light (CERCL), 1955-1988 (Box 6)
  Notes, clippings, Local 77 booklet, City Light publications and newsletters, IBEW ritual book and by-laws, blank forms, Cornish dues receipts and membership cards, documents from trainings and workshops, memos, legal documents, budgets, flyers and notices, meeting minutes, Affirmative Action Plan, reports, resumes, phone directories, IBEW contract, correspondence, newsletters, notes, and brochures
- Committee for Equal Rights at City Light (CERCL)- Press, 1983-1991 (Box 7)
  Announcements, clippings, and media sign-in sheet
- Committee for Equal Rights at City Light (CERCL)- General, 1985-1998 (Box 7)
  Clippings, correspondence, flyers, newsletter, song lyrics, notes, memos, case subject files, reports, legal documents, financial report, agendas, resume, Affirmative Action work plan, employee evaluations, meeting minutes, and performance worksheet
- Committee for Equal Rights at City Light (CERCL), 1984-2003 (Box 8)
  Clippings, notes, correspondence, memos, Local 77 by-laws, flyers, and conference announcement and schedule
- Committee for Equal Rights at City Light (CERCL)- Human Rights Department Case, 1984-1990 (Box 8)
  Correspondence, memos, statistics, legal documents, resolution, Washington State publications, and blank forms
- Ad Hoc Committee, 1983-1989 (Box 8)
  Reports, memos, correspondence, clippings, notes, agendas, meeting minutes, flyers, fact sheets, legal documents, and petitions
- Miscellaneous, 1983-1993 (Box 8)
  Notes, clippings, flyers, correspondence, legal documents, employee history cards, reports, memos, applications, job descriptions, and employee evaluations related to CERCL, employee cases, and Seattle Human Rights Commission/Department
- Miscellaneous, 1983-1988 (Box 9)
  Correspondence, memos, clippings, legal documents including witness statements, notes, KIRO news report, flyers, press packet, meeting minutes, training packets, employee evaluation, resolution, reports, and job description related to CERCL, Seattle Human Rights Department, and Seattle City Light